Guide to the Ithaca Woman's Club records,1897-1963.
Ithaca Woman's Club records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ithaca Woman's Club records, 1897-1963.
2743
Ithaca Woman's Club (Ithaca, N.Y.)
4.4 cubic ft.
Manuscript volumes, receipts, programs, historical summaries, news clippings, and a scrapbook.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records include three manuscript volumes containing constitution, by-laws, list of charter members; treasurers' records (1897-1909); and minutes of the Home Economic Section of the Ithaca Woman's Club (1902). Also miscellaneous items including receipts, programs, historical summaries, news clippings. One scrapbook containing a history of the club, lists of charter and early members, photographs of club presidents and copies of presidents' speeches and club brochures (1897-1949).
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records include three manuscript volumes containing constitution, by-laws, list of charter members; treasurers' records (1897-1909); and minutes of the Home Economic Section of the Ithaca Woman's Club (1902). Also miscellaneous items including receipts, programs, historical summaries, news clippings. One scrapbook containing a history of the club, lists of charter and early members, photographs of club presidents and copies of presidents' speeches and club brochures (1897-1949).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ithaca Woman's Club (Ithaca, N.Y.); Ithaca Woman's Club (Ithaca, N.Y.) Home Economic Section.
Subjects:
Home economics.; Women--Ithaca (N.Y.)--Societies and clubs.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Tompkins County (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Clippings.; Minutes.; Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Large scrapbook compiled by Mrs. A.E.M. Hasbrouck and presented to the Ithaca Woman's Club in 1928. Contains typed history of the Club, list of Charter and Earliest Members for as far as was known at that date, photographs of: (Box 1)
  Mrs. Hasbrouck
  Mrs. Charles Crandall
  Miss Charity Smith
  Mrs. Louisa Riley (2) and her home on University Avenue
  The Lewis Home, 444 N. Aurora St. (where Club was organized)
  Later photographs include:
  Mrs. Jamie Messenger
  Juanita B. Bates
  Mrs. J.A. Winans
  Lelle Rhodes Mangang
  Mary M. Denton
  Mrs. Sidney L. Howell
  Sarah L. Osborn
  Viola B. Lent
  Maude Coleman Walker
  Margaret L. Head
  Mrs. Thomas J. Parker
  Alice D. Smiley
  Anna Ball Cary (Mrs. Elmer E.)
  Gratia Mungle
  Isabel B. Doyle
  Mrs. Alfred H. Butwell
  Mrs. David Perry
  Minnie W. Muenscher
  Veta A. Butterworth
  Mrs. A.L. Winsor
  and groups.
  (All the foregoing were presidents.)
  This scrapbook also contains copies of the presidents' speeches and brochures of the club through various years. The first program is dated 1896-1897 and series runs through to 1948-1949.
- "New Crusader" Yearbooks + Journal Writeups, 1915-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 03/1909 - 03/1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Secretary's Report of Meetings of Ithaca Women's Club, 04/1914-03/1921 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club. Note: Minutes from Oct 3 1921 to Sept 1942 were burnt when Secretary left town (with approval of President), 10/1921-05/1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 09/1921-12/1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 01/1948-06/1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 05/1952-02/1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 02/1958-04/1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 05/1964-12/1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 01/1971-10/1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 11/1976-12/1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 12/1984-10/1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Meeting Minutes Ithaca Women's Club, 11/1996-06/2010 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Member Lists in annual booklets, 1985-2010 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Constitution and bylaws in annual booklets, 1915-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Card catalogue of resigned members, deceased in back (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Card catalogue of active/current members (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Card catalogue of former, life and deceased members (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Social Chairman's Records, 1935-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Minutes for 5th Household Arts Group of Women's Club, 1949-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Treasurer?s Reports Household Arts, 1967-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Second Division Household Arts Minutes + Old Correspondence, 1947-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Corresponding Secretary cash records notebook, 1911-1912 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- First Literature Department Notebook, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Treasure Report, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Antique Study Group Programs, 1957-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Second Drama Division Annual Report, 1978-1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Second Literature Department Annual Program, 1978-1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Second Literature Department Notebook, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Second Literature Department Programs + Notebook, 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Second Literature Department Notebook, 1938-1946 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Antique Study Group Minutes and Attendance Records, 1949-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Household Arts Group, 1983-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Chairman of Committees Bylaws, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Committee Reports, 1969-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Community Improvement Project, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- First Literature Department Meeting Book, 1950-1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Secretary-Treasurer's Book of the Second Division of Household Arts, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- First Literature Group Treasury Book, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Literature Department Book, 1963-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Women's Community Building Treasurer's Reports, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Community Improvement Program Report, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Ithaca Women?s Club Receipts Book, 1962-1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Ithaca Women's Club Receipts Book, 1972-1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Income and Expenses Ledger, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Awards and Memoranda I, 1968-2005 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Awards and Memoranda II, 1968-2005 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Second Drama Division Notebook, 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- In Remembrance Book, 1957-2009 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Secretary Book, 1961-1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Parliamentary Practice Book, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Burgess Excerpts (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Scrapbook, 1925-1946 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1946-1962 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
- Small manuscript volume of Constitution and By-Laws, also contains list of charter members. (This volume has the following inscription: "This is to record that this constitution is in my father's handwriting" (signed) Howard Wait Riley, June 5, 1967). This volume also contains the Revised Constitution of June 1, 1903 (Box 5)
- Small manuscript volume - Treasurer's Book, 1897-1909 (Box 5)
- IWC Constitution, 1915-1916 (Box 5)
- Minute book of the Home Economic Section of the Ithaca Woman's Club, 1902 (Box 5)
  This book consists of typed and mimeographed copies of minutes of meetings, outlines of talks given by various people on different topics such as:
  Development of the Home
  Books and Pictures in the Home
  Artistic Homes
  Some Advantages of Vegetarianism (etc.)
  People mentioned as giving talks:
  Martha Van Rensselaer
  Mrs. Effie D. Morse
  Mrs. John Gifford
  Professor Carpenter
  Dr. Wilder
  Prof. V.A. Moore
  Mrs. M.V. Slingerland
- Two page handwritten information about Mrs. Louisa L. Riley, organizer of the Ithaca Woman's Club in 1895 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Receipted bill for $15.00 for programs from Atkinson and Mitchell, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Receipt from New York State Federation of Women's Clubs for dues, 1908-1909 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Receipt from Western New York Federation of Women's Clubs, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Ithaca Woman's Club, Twentieth Anniversary Dinner program, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Constitution and By-Laws, Ithaca Woman's Club, revised, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Note about the gavel presented to the Club by Mrs. E.A. Denton, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Poem by Mary M. Denton, written originally for the Woman's Club Conservation Dinner, 1918-04-29, seven months before the Armistice was signed. Repeated at the fortieth anniversary, 1935-12-2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Ten pages (typed), "A History of the Woman's Club," written for the Fortieth Anniversary Banquet, Mary M. Denton, 1935-12-02 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Four pages (carbon typescript), about the Woman's Club, written for the Fortieth Anniversary, by (Mrs.) G.D. Hopkins., 1935-12-02 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- News clipping from New York Times, regarding the founding of the Woman's Club of Orange, New Jersey, at Mrs. Louisa L. Riley's home in 1872, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Four page carbon typescript, "History of the Ithaca Woman's Club," written by Ada E. Hasbrouck, a charter member. For the Fortieth Anniversary in. Contains list of Charter and Earliest Members, so far as known, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Letter to "Dear Maude" from Alice M (?- née Myers?), 1945-05-09 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Resolutions (carbon typescript) adopted at Club meeting, 1963-04-01 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Two negatives of the group pictures in Scrapbook (Box 5, Folder 1)